In this unit, we're going to talk about
the very basic thing that a computer does,
which is execute one
instruction after the other.
We're going to look more specifically
at how exactly is that done.
Well, really, it's very simple.
You first fetch the instruction
that you need to execute, and
then you just execute it.
And then you repeat.
And that's the only thing that a CPU does.
Fetch an instruction, execute it, fetch
another instruction, execute it, and so
on and so forth.
So let us look specifically at each of
these two stages, what it exactly happens
there and how does that translate
into what happens in hardware.
So let's first talk about fetching.
So, how do you get the neck,
next instruction that you need to execute.
Well, where is the next
instruction located at?
It's in the program memory,
it's in the memory.
Where in the memory?
In the address that's specified
by our program counter, probably.
So, we need to basically put
the location of the next instruction,
of the instruction that
you want to execute next,
into the address of the program memory.
And then we need to read
the contents of that memory and
then we will get the basic
instructions that we need to execute,
the code of the instructions
that we need to execute.
The next instruction will
usually just be the one after
the one that we just did in the previous.
That is if we now finished
instruction number eight,
usually the next instruction
will be instruction number nine.
Sometimes we already know that we jump and
we're going to need,
want to execute the different instruction.
So how do we actually go about putting
the address of the next instruction
into the address input
of the program memory?
Well, we're going to have to put it
somewhere and that's going to be into some
counter, into some register and that
is usually called the program counter.
So basically the hard words of exec,
executes the fetch,
if you wish, part of the cycle is
the following, there is a program counter,
when we need to jump into a new location
or we need to just increase and
go to the next instruction, we need
to manipulate the program counter so
it will have the address
of the next instruction.
The output of the program counter
feeds into the address specification
of our program memory.
And then,
out of the program memories output
comes the actual code of instructions
that we need to execute.
So that is basically what happens in the
fetch part of the fetch and execute cycle.
So now, once we have the code of the
instruction, now we need to execute it.
So the instruction code itself has all the
specifics of what we're going to do now.
Which a,
calculations that we're supposed to do.
Are we touching this register or
that register and so on.
And whether we want to,
need to jump afterwards and so on.
So usually all that information is coded
somehow inside the instructions that
we already have because that we
got it in the instruction part
in the fetch part of the cycle.
And usually the way it's
coded is in a simple way.
So that is basically,
different parts of the instruction,
bits, actually control the different
parts that we need to do right now.
Sometimes it's more complicated, sometimes
it's more simple but that's a basic idea.
So the basic execution executing
the current instruction basically mean
taking the bits from the instruction
code that specifies what to do, and
actually doing what needs to be done.
Looking at it in the hardware phase,
from the hardware point of view, the
instruction we already got from our fetch,
that is now going to feed into the control
bus of our CPU, of our computer.
And that control bus,
basically controls everything.
It tell the ALU what instruction
to compute, to add numbers,
subtract them, or so on.
It also tells where do the,
data pieces come from.
Do they come from which which register or
from the data memory or so on.
So we basically have the instruction
memory that we just fetched, basically
tells us exactly each part of the system
what to do right now in the execute cycle.
And that really controls whether
we read from the data memory,
whether we read from the registers, what
do we compute, where to write and so on?
Of course there are many details.
How is that exactly done?
How do we, how does the bytes from
the instructions specifically
tell the ALU what to do which
registers to choose and so on?
That is best a, viewed through
the lens of a particular computer.
Specifically we will actually
get into these details
when we talk about our computer,
about the HACK computer.
And that is what we are going to do,
be doing the next few units
where you're actually going to see
how we actually control each and
every part of the system
from the instruction bits.
So, we're not going to delve deeper
into the specifics of this part,
which is really the most, more, most of
the work that is done and by the computer.
But rather, I want to take a step
backwards and look at a certain problem
that I've sort of glossed over so
far, and that is the fact
that we really have a clash between
the fetch cycle and the execute cycle.
You see, both the program and
the data reside in memory.
In the fetch cycle, basically we
need to get from the program memory,
the next instruction.
So we need to put into
the address of the memory,
the address of the next instruction and
get the instructions output.
On the other hand, in the execute cycle,
we need to access data that
also resides in memory.
So we need to put into
the address of the memory,
the address of the data piece
that we want to operate on,
which has nothing to do with the program
piece that gave us the instruction.
And because we have a single memory,
that is a clash,
because what are we going to put into
the address, are we going to put there,
the pro, the address of the instruction,
or is address of the data piece?
We need to do both and that's a problem.
So how do we solve that?
Well, basically we are going to do one
after the other, that is the usual way.
How do we do one after the other?
There's going to be a multiplexer that
feeds into the address of the memory.
In the first part of the cycle in the
fetch cycle, we're going to actually set
the multiplexer to plug into
the address input of the memory,
the program counter that is
the location of the next instruction.
While in the execute cycle,
the multiplexer will actually set
the memory to actually point into
the data address that we need to access.
And of course, the output of
the memory will go into both places.
Both into the, the bit part of this
system that needs instruction and
into the part of the system that are used
inside when executing to actually put
information there.
A, you may wonder, okay, so
how do we do both of them together?
Well, when you look at it
you really need to remember
the instruction from the fetch cycle
to used for the execution cycle.
So that is what we're going to do.
When we actually a,
are in the fetch cycle,
we put the address of the next
instruction, we get the next instruction,
and then we need to remember it
inside an instruction register.
And that instruction register
is exactly what is remains
holding the value of the instruction that
we're now executing in the execute cycle.
And then of course, in the execute cycle
now we have the instruction already stored
in this register.
And we can work with all the information
that we need a, for the execute cycle
using the data memory that is being
addressed in the second part of the cycle.
So, this is the usual way it's done.
Now there is a shortcut and
that is simply keep the two different
parts of the memory separate.
That is,
have one unit holding the data memory and
another unit holding the program memory.
Each one of these units
has its own address.
And then we don't need to worry about,
a, be,
between switching between them,
a, as we've just shown.
Eh, this shortcut makes everything simple.
It is sometimes called the Harvard
architecture, but we just view it as
a variant of the von Neumann Architecture
and keep using it due to its simplicity.
So, now we've basically finished
talking about the general a,
architecture of computers.
How in general do you actually a,
construct a computer?
What we're going to switch in
the next unit is talking specifically
about our HACK computer.
And how it is built a, exactly.